One of the first times an American was ever brought over to Japan to lead a professional Japanese baseball team, Bobby Valentine, in 1995, he took this really mediocre squad, he lead them to a stunning second-place finish, and he was instantly fired. Why? "Well," said the team spokesman, "because of his emphasis on winning." (Laughter) Official Japan can feel quite a lot like that point that was said to last two hours and 12 minutes, and playing not to lose can take all the imagination, the daring, the excitement, out of things. At the same time, playing ping-pong in Japan reminds me why choirs regularly enjoy more fun than soloists. In a choir, your only job is to play your small part perfectly, to hit your notes with feeling, and by so doing, to help to create a beautiful harmony that's much greater than the sum of its parts. Yes, every choir does need a conductor, but I think a choir releases you from a child's simple sense of either-ors. You come to see that the opposite of winning isn't losing -- it's failing to see the larger picture. As my life goes on, I'm really startled to see that no event can properly be assessed for years after it has unfolded. I once lost everything I owned in the world, every last thing, in a wildfire. But in time, I came to see that it was that seeming loss that allowed me to live on the earth more gently, to write without notes, and actually, to move to Japan and the inner health club known as the ping-pong table. Conversely, I once stumbled into the perfect job, and I came to see that seeming happiness can stand in the way of true joy even more than misery does. Playing doubles in Japan really relieves me of all my anxiety, and at the end of an evening, I notice everybody is filing out in a more or less equal state of delight. I'm reminded every night that not getting ahead isn't the same thing as falling behind any more than not being lively is the same thing as being dead. And I've come to understand why it is that Chinese universities are said to offer degrees in ping-pong, and why researchers have found that ping-pong can actually help a little with mild mental disorders and even autism. But as I watch the 2020 Olympics in Tokyo, I'm going to be keenly aware that it won't be possible to tell who's won or who's lost for a very long time. You remember that point I mentioned that was said to last for two hours and 12 minutes? Well, one of the players from that game ended up, six years later, in the concentration camps of Auschwitz and Dachau. But he walked out alive. Why? Simply because a guard in the gas chamber recognized him from his ping-pong playing days. Had he been the winner of that epic match? It hardly mattered. As you recall, many people had filed out before even the first point was concluded. The only thing that saved him was the fact that he took part. The best way to win any game, Japan tells me every other night, is never, never to think about the score. Thank you. (Applause)
Una de las primeras veces que trajeron a un estadounidense a Japón para que dirigiera un equipo de béisbol japonés profesional, Bobby Valentine, en 1995, se encargó de un equipo muy mediocre, lo llevó a que finalizara en segundo lugar, y lo despidieron instantáneamente. ¿Por qué? "Bueno," dijo el portavoz del equipo, "a causa de su insistencia en ganar". (Risas) El Japón oficial puede parecerse mucho a ese punto que supuestamente duró dos horas y 12 minutos, y jugar para no perder puede quitar la imaginación, la audacia y el placer de todo. Al mismo tiempo, jugar al pimpón en Japón me recuerda por qué los coros se divierten mucho más que los solistas. En un coro, su único trabajo es cantar su parte perfectamente, llegar a sus notas con emoción, y así poder ayudar a crear una magnífica armonía que es mucho más poderosa que la suma de sus partes. Sí, cada coro necesita un director de orquesta, pero creo que un coro los libera del simple sentido de un niño de uno u otro. Se llega a comprender que lo contrario de ganar no es perder, es negarse a ver la situación en su conjunto. Conforme pasa mi vida, me alarma mucho que acontecimientos tarden tantos años en evaluarse adecuadamente. Un día, perdí todo lo que poseía, absolutamente todo, en un incendio. Pero con el tiempo, llegué a entender que fue esa pérdida aparente lo que me permitió vivir en la Tierra más tranquilamente, escribir sin notas, y mudarme a Japón donde hay ese centro deportivo interior conocido como la mesa de pimpón. Por el contrario, una vez encontré por accidente el trabajo perfecto, y llegué a entender que esa felicidad aparente puede obstaculizar la verdadera alegría incluso más que la tristeza. Jugar dobles en Japón me libera de toda mi ansiedad, y al final de una tarde, noto que todos salen en un estado de deleite más o menos parecido. Todas las tardes me recuerdan que no salir adelante no es lo mismo que quedarse atrás que no estar lleno de vida no equivale a estar muerto. He llegado a comprender por qué se dice que las universidades chinas ofrecen diplomas en pimpón, y por qué investigadores han afirmado que el pimpón puede ayudar un poquito con trastornos mentales leves e incluso con el autismo. Pero cuando vea las Olimpiadas de 2020 en Tokio, estaré completamente consciente de que no será posible diferenciar los ganadores de los perdedores durante mucho tiempo. ¿Recuerdan ese punto que mencioné que supuestamente duró dos horas y 12 minutos? Uno de los jugadores de ese partido terminó, seis años más tarde, en los campos de concentración de Auschwitz y Dachau. Pero salió con vida. ¿Por qué? Sencillamente porque un guardia en la cámara de gas lo reconoció de sus días como jugador de pimpón. ¿Había ganado ese épico partido? Apenas importaba. Como recuerdan, mucha gente había salido antes de que se terminara el primer punto. Lo único que le salvó la vida fue el hecho de que había participado. La mejor manera de ganar cualquier partido, me dice Japón cada dos tardes, es nunca, nunca pensar en el marcador. Gracias. (Aplausos)